<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="./_c74_tut.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<chapter name="How to install MaxScore">
<previous name="00maxscore-01welcome">Welcome to MaxScore!</previous>
<next name="01maxscore-userInterface">MaxScore: The User Interface</next>

<parent name="00maxscore-00index">MaxScore: Table of Contents</parent>

<h1>How to install MaxScore</h1>

<h2><b>1. Start</b></h2>

<p>To uninstall a previously version of MaxScore run the Uninstaller which you'll find in Max 8/Uninstallers/MaxScore. MaxScore requires Max 8.1.8 and higher.</p>

<p>Important info for Max 8 users upgrading from Max 7: If your old MaxScore package was automatically copied to the Max 8 packages folder, please remove it before installing a recent version of MaxScore.</p>
<p><i>After downloading the installer, open the file. You will first see a splash screen with the MaxScore logo and a text window informing you about the steps you’re about to take.</i></p>

<p><illustration><img src="images/installation/01MaxScoreSetup.png"/></illustration></p>
<p><i>Click OK and click the Next button in the installer window underneath.</i></p>

<p><illustration><img src="images/installation/02MaxScoreLicense.png"/></illustration></p>
<p><i>Accept the license agreement and click on Next.</i></p>

<p>On the next window, click on the folder icon and navigate to the location of Max folder you want to install MaxScore into. </p>
<p>Max 8 and Live 10 and higher:</p>
<p>The best choice for your MaxScore installation is /Users/[your_home_folder]/Documents/Max 8/ (macOS) or C:Users[your_user_name]DocumentsMax 8 (Windows).</p>

<p><b>Refer to the Max documentation if you choose to install MaxScore into another Max 8 folder besides the one indicated above. DO NOT create your own Max 8 folders as Max or Live may not be able to find the files if those folders have not originally been created by Max itself.</b></p>
<p><illustration><img src="images/installation/03MaxScoreInstallationMode.png"/></illustration></p>

<p>After clicking Next, decide on the type of installation (Minimal = MaxScore for Max only; Full = MaxScore and LiveScore for Ableton Live).</p>
<p><illustration><img src="images/installation/04MaxScoreReady.png"/></illustration></p>
<p>The installer is now ready to install MaxScore on your computer.</p>

<h2><b>2. Location of installed files</b></h2>
<p>puts files into</p>
<ul>
  <li>Max resources into a folder called MaxScore in [path_to_Max_folder]>Packages.</li>
  <li>Ableton Live files into a folder called LiveScore in [path_to_Ableton_folder]>User Library.</li>
</ul>

<!--
<seealsolist>
<seealso name="js">Max JavaScript object</seealso>
<seealso name="jsintro" type="vignette" module="js" >javascriptinmax</seealso>
</seealsolist>
-->
</chapter>
