<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="./_c74_tut.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<chapter name="MaxScore Editor: First Steps">

<previous name="00maxscore-tour">How to install MaxScore</previous>
<next name="03maxscore-StaffManager">MaxScore Editor: Staff Manager</next>
<parent name="00maxscore-00index">MaxScore: Table of Contents</parent>


<h1>MaxScore Editor: First Steps</h1>

<h2>Introduction</h2>

<p>
  The MaxScore Editor is a GUI designed for editing MaxScore scores directly in a Max patcher window. The backbone of the Editor is the <o>MaxScore</o> mxj object which implements the <a href="http://www.algomusic.com/jmsl/jmslhome.html">Java Music Specification Language</a> in Max.
</p>

<h2>Initialization</h2>

<p>In this tutorial, we will get familiar with the GUI of the MaxScore Editor and introduce its basic functions.</p>

<p>Access <o>Maxscore.Editor</o> by right-clicking on an empty space of an unlocked Max patcher window, then select “Paste From>MaxScore>Editors>maxscore.editor.clipping.maxpat”. You are now ready to start working on a new project.</p>
<p>Lock the patcher and open the Editor window by clicking on the “Open Editor” button inside the <o>bpatcher</o>.
<illustration><img src="images/UserInterface-basics/editor-01-basics-1.png"/></illustration></p>

<h2>The MaxScore Editor Window</h2>
<illustration><img src="images/Basics/MaxScore-Tutorial-Editor.png" width="700"/></illustration>

<ul>
  <li>Welcome to the Max Editor window! On the upper left-hand side you will see the <b>Menu Bar</b> where you can access various functions.</li>
  <li>Look at the <b>Sidebar</b> on the right. There are four tabs, <b>Tools</b>, <b>Pitch Utility</b>, <b>Scorpions</b> and <b>Picster</b>. In this tutorial we will look at functions in the first two. We will go over the others in the next tutorials.</li>
  <li>Now click on File>New Score from <b>MaxScore's</b> Menu Bar.</li>
</ul>
  <illustration><img src="images/UserInterface-basics/editor-01-basics-2.png" width="200"/></illustration>
<techdetail>
  <p>In the main canvas, you will see the <b>Score View</b>, where you will create and edit your scores. You can always return to this page by pressing Shift-1.</p>
  <p>Press Shift-2 to go to the <b>Staff View</b>. Here you can customize your staves with various attributes.</p>
  <p>Press Shift-3 for the <b>Preferences</b>, where you can change various other score attributes.</p>
</techdetail>
<h2>Hello World</h2>

  <p>Now let's create our first score!</p>
  <p>By default, the tempo is set to 60 BPM, the time signature to 4/4 and the clef to a treble G-clef. To change this, use to the ‘Tools’ pane of the sidebar and make your choices accordingly.</p>
  <illustration><img src="images/UserInterface-basics/editor-01-basics-3.png"/></illustration>
  <p>To change the time signature, click on the ‘Meter’ button right below the clef box and enter number of beats and subdivision separated by a space, e.g ‘7 8’. Click the ‘Tempo’ button next to it to set the tempo, if desired.</p>
  <illustration><img src="images/UserInterface-basics/editor-01-basics-4.png" width="250"/></illustration>
  <p>Let's now add the first note. In order to add notes, double click or ctrl-click on a blank space on the designated measure (otherwise you might add an interval to an already existing note). The note is blue which means it is selected. If you want to transpose notes, you can either cmd-drag (Mac) or ctrl-drag (Windows), or use the keyboard shortcuts u, j, i, k, o, l for respective transpositions. You can always access the list of shortcuts from the menu: "Edit>Shortcuts".</p>
  <illustration><img src="images/UserInterface-basics/editor-01-basics-5.png" width="600"/></illustration>
  <p>To convert a note into a rest, click the rest button on top of the third column in the Tools panel, or alternatively use the keyboard shortcut r.</p>
  <p>To add dynamics or articulation, select a note and then choose from the Tools bar the corresponding symbols. e.g. for dynamics check the 5th column.</p>
  <p>If you wish to add a crescendo or decrescendo to your score, drag-enclose the notes to which you want this to apply and click the respective symbols from the Tools pane.</p>
  <p>If you want to turn your notes into tuplets, select the notes and then choose the corresponding symbols from the Tools pane (5th and 6th columns, ‘3’, ‘5’, ‘7’, ‘9’, etc.)</p>
  <p>To add repeats or barlines, select the measure and then click on the corresponding symbols at the bottom of the Tools pane.</p>
  <p>Go to the Editor Preferences (shift-3) to enable the display of the title and to enter the title, subtitled and composer info to be displayed on the top of your score.</p>
<illustration><img src="images/UserInterface-basics/editor-01-1st_example.png"/></illustration>

<p>For larger scores, navigate through the score by using the “Navigation” tool at the bottom of the window. Type the number of the page you wish to display or use the arrows to move to other measures (single arrows) or pages (double arrows).</p>
<p>Zoom in or out the score by changing the corresponding value for the “Zoom”.</p>

<!--

<seealsolist>
<seealso name="js">Max JavaScript object</seealso>
<seealso name="jsintro" type="vignette" module="js" >javascriptinmax</seealso>
</seealsolist> <-->

</chapter>
