<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="./_c74_tut.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<chapter name="MaxScore Editor: Preferences">
<previous name="03maxscore-StaffManager">MaxScore Editor: Staff Manager</previous>
<next name="03maxscore-Sidebar">MaxScore: Sidebar</next>
<parent name="00maxscore-00index">MaxScore: Table of Contents</parent>
<h1>MaxScore Editor: Preferences</h1>

<p><i>Shortcut: shift-3</i></p>
<illustration><img src="images/Basics/Preferences.png"/></illustration>

<p>To open the Preferences, go to “View” menu on the upper left-hand side of the window and choose “Preferences”, or use the shortcut Shift-3.
In the Preferences window, you can set the canvas size as well as change the title and subtitle of your project and add the name of the composer. You can choose to show this information on the score by clicking on the Show Title toggle. You also have the possibility customize the positioning of the entire score. Use the “Title Margin”, “Left Margin”, “Right Margin”, etc. options.
You can also choose to show or hide markings such as tempo, time signatures, key signatures etc. by setting the corresponding toggles. In addition, you can also customize your score by changing the color of the background or using another text or music font.
Hit the “Save Preferences” button on the bottom of the page, if you want to make your changes the new default.</p>

<p>This is a comprehensive list of the current options:</p>

<h2>Personal Information</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Title</li>
  <li>Subtitle</li>
  <li>Composer</li>
  <li>Copyright</li>
</ul>

<h2>Spacing:</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Canvas size</li>
  <li>Title Margin</li>
  <li>Left Margin</li>
  <li>Right Margin</li>
  <li>Top Margin</li>
  <li>Bottom Margin*</li>  
  <li>First System Indent <i> - indentation for the first system</i></li>
</ul>


<h2>Show or hide elements:</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Title</li>
  <li>Instruments</li>
  <li>Section Brackets</li>
  <li>Time Signatures</li>
  <li>Key signatures</li>
  <li>Staff Numbers</li>  
  <li>Measure Numbers</li>
  <li>Tempo</li>  
  <li>Clefs</li>
  <li>Courtesy Clefs</li>  
</ul>

<h2>Other customization options:</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Set Wrap <i>- on/off:  1 system per page</i></li>
  <li>Set Measure Number Offset <i>- enter a value for the measure number on the first measure in the score. </i></li>
  <li>Numbers on All Measures </li>
  <li>Set Hold Scaler <i> - change the default for the hold time parameter</i></li>  
  <li>Set Durational Spacing Base<i> - change the vertical spacing between notes. The higher the number the more equally the notes will be spaced.</i></li>
  <li>Use Legacy Multi Track Orientation</li>  
</ul>

<h2>Colors:</h2>
<ul>
<li>Selection Buffer Note color</li>
<li>Background Color</li>
<li>Foreground Color</li>
<li>Flashing Note Color</li>
</ul>

<h2>Fonts:</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Text Font</li>
  <li>Music Font <i> - we currently support the Bravura and Petaluma fonts</i></li>
</ul>

<h2>Default Picster Lib Folder.</h2>
<p>Set the path to your personal Picster Library</p>

<h2>Playback and Quantization:</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Playback in Overdrive</li>
  <li>Playback Advance Time (in seconds)</li>
  <li>Quantization - <i>from the first drop-down menu select a main duration (whole Note (W), half Note (H) or Quarter Note(Q)). From the number box dropping menu select the subdivision to which to quantize. Add modes, set the default or clear your setting with buttons to the right</i></li>
</ul>

<h2>Proportional Notation: </h2>
<p>Select a Time Unit (pixels/second) for scrolling. By default is "100"; the lowest possible value is "5".</p>

<h2>Saving Preferences: </h2>
<p><i>You can also save your preferences as a preset file by clicking “Save Preference as…” button. If this option is chosen, you can use them next time you create a new score by going to Preferences (shift-3) and selecting the preferred one by clicking on “Open Preferences”</i></p>
<p>By clicking on Attribute List you can inspect the MaxScore attributes being saved as preferences.</p>

</chapter>
