<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="./_c74_tut.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<chapter name="MaxScore Editor: Staff Manager">
<previous name="01maxscore-userInterface">MaxScore: The User Interface</previous>
<next name="03maxscore-preferencesView"></next>

<parent name="00maxscore-00index">MaxScore: Table of Contents</parent>


<h1>MaxScore Editor: Staff Manager</h1>

<p>In this chapter, we will learn how to customize a score in the Staff Manager. For this, open the MaxScore Editor and create a new score (refer to the previous chapter on how to do this).</p>

<p>If you wish to add a new staff go to the “Edit” menu on the upper left-hand side of the window and select “Add staff”. </p>
<p>You can now change the behaviour of each staff separately in the Staff Manager.</p>

<illustration><img src="images/Basics/StaffManager.png"/></illustration>

<p>Go to “View” on the left corner of the window and choose “Staff Manager”, or use the shortcut Shift-2. A GUI appears in the window which let you customize your staves. we will now explain every column in the Staff Manager.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Staff: You can always choose which staff will be displayed in which order. Choose the order by typing in the numbers in the “Staff” column. 
e.g. if you have 3 staffs and you want the second one to be displayed as the top one, type “2” “1” “3” in the different rows. The staves will be renumbered after sorting</li>
  <li>Group: If you want to group together two or more staffs, go the the “Group” column and type the same number for the staffs you wish to be displayed as a system.
e.g. if you have 3 staffs and you want the bottom two to exist as a system, type “0” “1” “1” in the different rows.</li>
<li>Instrument Name: You can specify the instrument’s name for each staff by clicking on the white space. Type the name of the instrument in the dialog that will pop up and press “OK”. You can also specify an abbreviation for the instrument’s name to appear an all staves but the first one by clicking on the second white space of each column and entering the abbreviated name. The number on the right refers to the vertical offset for both the instrument and abbreviated instrument names.</li>
<li>Clef: Choose a specific clef for each staff.</li>
<li>Key Signature: Choose a specific key signature for each staff</li>
<li>Transp.: Here you set the initial transposition that will be applied to the playback of this staff. Useful when notating transposing instruments.</li>
<li>Space Above/Below: Customize your score even further by setting the desired spacing between staves.</li>
<li>St.L.: Add stafflines above or below the 5-line staff.</li>
<li>L.L.: Show or hide ledger lines</li>
<li>Style: Apply a staff style such as percussion notation or tablature. Here you can also set the precision with which microtonal scales will be displayed. More info in the MaxScore: Styles chapter.</li>
<li>Print: Choose whether to include a particular staff in the print-out of the score. Use this option to print parts or instrumental sections.</li>
</ul>
<p>You can change the overall look and behavior of your score in Preferences (shift-2)</p>
 

</chapter>
