<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="./_c74_tut.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<chapter name="MaxScore: Graphics">
<previous name="07maxscore-microtones">MaxScore: Preferences</previous>
<next name="08maxscore-playback">Playback</next>
<parent name="00maxscore-00index">MaxScore: Table of Contents</parent>


<h1>MaxScore: Graphics</h1>

<p>MaxScore users can use the Picster mode to create and edit shapes on the fly.</p>
<p>MaxScore allows you to also attach shapes to measures or staves. This means that a shape will be shown automatically on every part should the score be split or rendered to multiple clients. It’s best used for global instructions that affect every members of an ensemble at once, such as tempo or overall dynamics. By using the canvas blankPageTransform 1 message, you can hide all score elements such as bar lines, clefs or staff lines and create purely graphical scores. The graphics will still have to be attached to either measure or staves whose areas show when clicked on the (now) empty space they usually occupy.</p>
<p>You can set the preference in the following 3 ways:</p>
<ul>
  <li>selecting a note / staff / measure in the canvas</li>
  <li>pressing s for staff or m for measure after selecting a note</li>
  <li>sending messages to the MaxScore abstraction (see the section "Creating and Editing Shapes via Messages")</li>
</ul>
<p>After selection, press Caps Lock to turn on Picster mode.</p>

<h2>Drawing modes</h2>
<p>Picster offers a variety of drawing tools. Once Picster mode is on (by pressing Caps Lock), you will see the name of the current drawing tool displayed in red on the top-left corner of the canvas.</p>

<techdetail>
<p>Select the desired drawing tool by pressing one of the following keys:</p>
<ul>
  <li><m>1</m>: line segment</li>
  <li><m>2</m>: rectangle</li>
  <li><m>3</m>: rounded rectangle</li>
  <li><m>4</m>: oval</li>
  <li><m>5</m>: arc</li>
  <li><m>6</m>: polygon</li>
  <li><m>7</m>: freehand</li>
  <li><m>8</m>: text</li>
  <li><m>9</m>: image</li>
  <li><m>0</m>: polycurve</li>
  <li><m>h</m>: hairpin</li>
  <li><m>b</m>: bracket</li>
</ul>
</techdetail>

<p>For most tools, click and drag in order to create shapes.</p>
<illustration><img src="images/Picster/picster-image1-small.png"/></illustration>
<illustration><img src="images/Picster/picster-image2-small.png"/></illustration>
<i>The name of a Picster tool appears in the upper left-hand corner after pressing caps lock. Drawn shapes will be attached to the top staff in this particular case.</i>

<h3><m>6</m>: polygon</h3>
<techdetail>
<p>A polygon requires a number of clicks. It will only complete after ctrl-clicking the canvas which closes its path.</p>
</techdetail>

<h3><m>8</m>: text</h3>
<techdetail>
<p>When the text tool is selected, a text box will pop up which can be written to. The text will appear in the score after clicking at the desired location.</p>

<illustration><img src="images/Picster/picster-image3-small.png"/></illustration>
<i>A text box opens when the text tool is selected.</i>

</techdetail>

<h3><m>9</m>: image</h3>
<techdetail>
<p>Bitmap and vector images can be placed with the image tool. Clicking on the canvas will open a file dialog and the image will be placed at the clicked location.</p>
</techdetail>

<h3><m>0</m>: polycurve</h3>
<techdetail>
<p>click or drag to create bezier curve nodes and handles. To delete the previous node, press shift once. To finish the shape, ctrl-click on the canvas. The end point will snap to the starting point if it's close enough (which creates a closed path).</p>
</techdetail>


<h2>Setting properties</h2>
<p>Before drawing the shape, some properties (color, pensize, etc) can be set by: </p>
<ul>
  <li>using the <link name="03maxscore-Sidebar">Picster tool</link> under the sidebar in the MaxScore Editor; or</li>
  <li>sending messages to the MaxScore abstraction. (See the section "Creating Shapes via Messages" below)</li>
</ul>

<illustration><img src="images/Picster/picster-image4-small.png"/></illustration>
<i>Color set to red</i>

<h2>Creating and Editing Shapes via Messages</h2>
<p>Picster is integrated in the MaxScore API. The MaxScore abstraction can receives messages for the creation of shapes. These messages have the same result as drawing the shapes by hand, i.e. select the elements the shapes are supposed to be attached to first and set properties before the shapes are created.</p>

<h3>Adding shapes to staves or measures</h3>
<p>MaxScore allows you to also attach shapes to measures or staves. This means that a shape will be shown automatically on every part should the score be split or rendered to multiple clients. It’s best used for global instructions that affect every members of an ensemble at once, such as tempo or overall dynamics.</p>
<p>Set the preference by sending the following messages:</p>

<ul>
  <li>picster preference staff</li>
  <li>picster preference measure</li>
  
</ul>

<h3>Setting properties</h3>
<p>Specify properties for the upcoming shape by sending the following messages:</p>
<techdetail>
  <ul>
    <li>
      <p><m>picster color <i>[r] [g] [b] [a]</i></m></p>
      <p>sets the color of the shape, each value from 0 to 1</p>
    </li>
    <li>
      <p><m>picster pensize <i>[p]</i></m></p>
      <p>sets line thickness in pixels</p>
    </li>
    <li>
      <p><m>picster arc <i>[start] [end]</i></m></p>
      <p>sets start and end points for arcs in radians</p>
    </li>
    <li>
      <p><m>picster roundedness <i>[r]</i></m></p>
      <p>sets the roundedness in pixels for a rounded rectangle</p>
    </li>
    <li>
      <p><m>picster font <i>[font]</i></m></p>
      <p>sets the font for texts</p>
    </li>
    <li>
      <p><m>picster fontsize <i>[fontsize]</i></m></p>
      <p>sets the font size for texts</p>
    </li>
    <li>
      <p><m>picster property <i>[property]</i></m></p>
      <p><m>stroke</m> or <m>fill</m>: determines whether a shape will be filled or not.</p>
    </li>
  </ul>
</techdetail>

<h3>Creating shapes</h3>
<p>Create a new shape by sending the following messages:</p>
<p>If the offsets are given in <i>numbers</i>, which will be applied in absolute coordinates relative to the canvas’s origin.</p>
<p>If the offsets are given as <m>. .</m>, the shape will be placed relative to the coordinates of a score element.</p>
<p>Example: <m>picster addShape . . line 20 20 50 70</m></p>
<techdetail>
<ul>
  <li>
    <p><m>picster addShape <i>[xoffset] [yoffset]</i> line <i>[x1] [x2] [y1] [y2]</i></m></p>
    <p>creates a line from (<m>x1</m>, <m>y1</m>) to (<m>x2</m>, <m>y2</m>)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><m>picster addShape <i>[xoffset] [yoffset]</i> rectangle <i>[x1] [x2] [y1] [y2]</i></m></p>
    <p>creates a rectangle from (<m>x1</m>, <m>y1</m>) to (<m>x2</m>, <m>y2</m>)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><m>picster addShape <i>[xoffset] [yoffset]</i> rounded_rectangle <i>[x1] [x2] [y1] [y2]</i></m></p>
    <p>creates a rounded rectangle from (<m>x1</m>, <m>y1</m>) to (<m>x2</m>, <m>y2</m>)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><m>picster addShape <i>[xoffset] [yoffset]</i> oval <i>[x1] [x2] [y1] [y2]</i></m></p>
    <p>creates an oval from (<m>x1</m>, <m>y1</m>) to (<m>x2</m>, <m>y2</m>)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><m>picster addShape <i>[xoffset] [yoffset]</i> arc <i>[x1] [x2] [y1] [y2]</i></m></p>
    <p>creates an arc from (<m>x1</m>, <m>y1</m>) to (<m>x2</m>, <m>y2</m>)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><m>picster addShape <i>[xoffset] [yoffset]</i> polygon <i>[x1] [x2] [y1] [y2] ... [xn] [yn]</i></m></p>
    <p>creates a closed polygon with corners at (<m>x1</m>, <m>y1</m>), (<m>x2</m>, <m>y2</m>), ...  (<m>xn</m>, <m>yn</m>).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><m>picster addShape <i>[xoffset] [yoffset]</i> polyline <i>[x1] [x2] [y1] [y2]</i></m></p>
    <p>creates a polyline with corners at (<m>x1</m>, <m>y1</m>), (<m>x2</m>, <m>y2</m>), ...  (<m>xn</m>, <m>yn</m>).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><m>picster addShape <i>[xoffset] [yoffset]</i> text <i>[textstring]</i></m></p>
    <p>creates a text element with the string <m>textstring</m></p>
    <p>Example: <m>picster addShape . . text “what’s up”</m></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><m>picster addShape <i>[xoffset] [yoffset]</i> image <i>[path]</i></m></p>
    <p>creates an image from the <m>path</m></p>
    <p>Supported image types: PNG, TIFF, JPEG, SVG</p>
  </li>
</ul>
</techdetail>

<h3>Picster Expressions</h3>
<p>Picster expressions are in the Max <o>dict</o> format. You can add expressions to or remove expressions from an existing Picster shape.</p>
<techdetail>
  <ul>
    <li>
      <p><m>picster addExpressionToSelectedShape dictionary <i>[name]</i></m></p>
      <p>adds Picster expression stored in the dict with name <m>[name]</m> to the selected shape</p>
    </li>
    <li>
      <p><m>picster removeAllExpressionsFromSelectedShape</m></p>
      <p>removes all expressions from the selected shape</p>
    </li>
  </ul>
</techdetail>

<h3>Button mode</h3>
<techdetail>
  <ul>
    <li>
      <p><m>picster buttonmode <i>[n]</i></m></p>
      <p><m>1</m> or <m>0</m>, turns button mode on or off</p>
    </li>
  </ul>
</techdetail>

<h3>Transforming an existing shape</h3>
<techdetail>
  <ul>
    <li>
      <p><m>picster rotate <i>[theta]</i></m></p>
      <p>rotates the selected shape by <m>theta</m> degrees</p>
    </li>
  </ul>
</techdetail>


<h2>Selecting, moving and deleting shapes</h2>

<p>When a shaped is clicked on, a red bounding rectangle will appear and the shape can be moved by dragging the rectangle to another location. Should shapes overlap, the “covered” shapes can be selected by repeatedly ctrl-clicking on them. The bounding rectangle will change its shape accordingly. Selected shapes can be deleted with the delete key.</p>

<illustration><img src="images/Picster/picster-image5-small.png"/></illustration>
<i>Figure 5. Clicking on an object will selected it. It can now be moved, deleted or edited.</i>

<illustration><img src="images/Picster/picster-image6-small.png"/></illustration>
<p></p>
<illustration><img src="images/Picster/picster-image7-small.png"/></illustration>
<i>Figure 6 and 7: Select overlapping shapes by ctrl-clicking on the canvas</i>


<h2>Copy, cut and paste</h2>
<p>A shape can be copied, cut and pasted and thus attached to a different score element. Use the c, x and v keys in Picster mode, but be aware of the fact that in order to select another score element, Picster mode needs to be first toggled off. Once the element is selected, Picster mode should to be activated again.</p>


<h2>Editing</h2>
<p>Once a shape is selected it can also be edited after pressing the e (“edit”) key. This will open a text editor showing the properties of the shape in JSON format. The changes can be finalized by pressing the u (“update”) key. Note that if the fill property is supposed to be changed from fill to stroke or vice versa, the id (2nd line) of the shape will also need to be changed in order to take effect, i.e. a paintrect will have to be renamed to framerect, a paintoval to frameoval and so on.</p>

<illustration><img src="images/Picster/picster-image8-small.png"/></illustration>
<i>Figure 8: Changes in the editor will take effect after closing the window and pressing the u key.</i>

<illustration><img src="images/Picster/picster-image9-small.png"/></illustration>
<i>Figure 9: Changing the "transform" property for example to [ 0.5, 0, 0, 0.5, 0, 0 ] will shrink the image to half its size.</i>

<h2>Adding Expressions</h2>
<p>You can add an expression to a shape if you want the expression to be sent when you either click on a shape (all types), or click on the note/interval the shape is attached to. Note and interval will also play their expressions during playback.</p>
<p>An expression is a sub dictionary which contains four keys:</p>

<ul class="dashed">
  <li>editor: currently inactive</li>
  <li>message: the message to be sent, e.g. sfplay</li>
  <li>value: value of the message, e.g. snare.mp3</li>
  <li>autorender : currently inactive</li>
  
</ul>

<p>To add an expression to a shape, select it first and send a message composed of the following items:</p>


<ul>
  <li>picster addExpressionToSelectedShape dictionary dictionary-name</li>  
</ul>

<p>dictionary-name being the name of the dictionary containing the four keys. The message also goes into the left-most inlet of bcanvas.</p>

<illustration><img src="images/Picster/picster-image10-small.png"/></illustration>
<p></p>
<i>Figure 10: Example for how to create a dictionary of an expression to be added to a Picster shape.</i>



</chapter>
