<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="./_c74_tut.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<chapter name="MaxScore: Staff Styles">
<previous name="05maxscore-scorepions">Macaque</previous>
<next name="08maxscore-playback">MaxScore: Playback</next>

<parent name="00maxscore-00index">MaxScore: Table of Contents</parent>


<h1>MaxScore: Staff Styles</h1>

<p>The MaxScore and LiveScore Editors were designed with microtones in mind, with the capability of representing pitch with virtually unlimited precision. The editor offers notation in various staff styles, quarter-tone, eighth-tone, 12th-tone and 16th-tone and Extended Helmholtz-Ellis JI Pitch notation among them, as well as cent precision playback via MaxScore Sampler or MaxScore Fluidsynth. </p>
<p>One of the unique features of the Editor is the seamless switch between notation styles such as different representations of the Bohlen-Pierce scale.</p>

<h2>Staff Styles and Pitch Utility</h2>

<illustration><img src="images/Microtones/micro-image0-style-menu-Pitch-tool.png" width="250"/></illustration>

<p>Four of the styles (to be set in the StaffManager style menu) sport their own editor windows which will be displayed in the sidebar's Pitch Utility when the MaxScore Editor is in Staff Manager view:
<ul>
<li>BP Chromatic</li>
<li>ClefDesigner</li>
<li>Percussion</li>
<li>Tablature</li>
</ul>
</p>
<illustration><img src="images/Microtones/ClefDesigner.png" width="250"/></illustration>


<h2>Setting and Transposing Pitches</h2>
<p>The Pitch Utility displays the pitch of a note when clicked. It also allows you to change its enharmonic spelling as well as to set and transpose it in cent precision. 
</p>

<h2>Labels</h2>
<p>Each note can also be labeled either according to its pitch, frequency or ratio in respect to given fundamental. N.B.: Labels update dynamically if the pitch of the note changes.</p>
<p><br/> </p>
<illustration><img src="images/Microtones/micro-image2-labels-Pitch-tool.png"/></illustration>

<h2>Keyboards</h2>
<p><br/>The editor comes with a number of virtual "keyboards " which will let you choose a tuning and conveniently enter of its pitches. "Keyboards" are Max patches that can be created and added to the MaxScore 8/patchers/keyboards folder from where they will be loaded when selected from the Entry Tools menu. The corresponding pitch will be sent out to a playback device when entering a note from a "keyboard. "</p>

<!--
<illustration><img src="images/Microtones/micro-image3-Keyboard-Pitch-tool.png"/></illustration>
<p><i>MIDI Input for standard tuning</i></p>
-->
<h3>nTET-entry tool</h3>
<p><br/>The nTET-entry tool can be used to input pitches of equidistant scales within arbitrary frame intervals.</p>
<p>Its Action menu contains following items: Add Note, Add Interval, Set Pitch, Set Transposition Interval, Play Thru, Approximate and Copy Scale. Add Note adds a new note, Add Interval adds an interval to an existing note and Set Pitch changes the note/interval to the desired pitch. Set Transposition Interval set the Pitch Tool's transposition interval to the interval between the clicked pitch and the first note of the tuning. When Play Thru is selected the pitch will be heard with note entry and Approximate allows you to approximate selected notes to the pitches of the chosen tuning. Copy Scale puts all pitches on the MaxScore clipboard from which they can be pasted into other scores.</p>
<p><br/> </p>
<illustration><img src="images/Microtones/micro-image4-nTET-entry-Pitch-tool.png" width="550"/></illustration>
<p><i>nTET-entry: Keyboard for equidistant tunings.</i></p>

<h3>Scala Browser</h3>
<p>The Scala Browser supports the Scala archive with 4600+ scales by offering search functions and a flexible microtonal display.</p>
<illustration><img src="images/Microtones/micro-image7-ScalaBrowser-Pitch-tool.png" width="600"/></illustration>
<p><i>he Scala Browser</i></p>

<h3>JI-entry tool</h3>
<p>The Pitch Utility allows you to set as well as add notes and intervals in terms of just intonation ratios.</p>
<p>A ratio can also be defined manually if not contained in the interval menu. Choosing "enter manually " on the top will open a dialog letting you define the desired ratio.</p>
<p>Use the up/down button to set the ratio and its direction.</p>
<p>The intervals menu uses the list of intervals from the Huygens-Fokker website. There are a few modes that need a bit of explanation:</p>
<ol>
<li>Add Note adds a note in respect to the current key area (C major if no other key area is specified) and octave range (4 = one-line octave). Therefore, if you select "3/2 perfect fifth " the note will be G in C major and E in A major.</li>
<li>Set Pitch sets the pitch of a note or interval in respect to the current key areaand octave range.</li>
<li>Add Interval adds an interval in respect to the current key area and octave range.</li>
<li>Stack Interval adds an interval in respect to the selected note or interval.</li>
<li>Transpose transposes a note/interval by the amount expressed by the ratio.</li>
</ol>
<illustration><img src="images/Microtones/micro-image8-JI-entry-Pitch-tool.png" width="450"/></illustration>
<p><i>JI-entry: Keyboard for the entry of JI interval. These intervals can be displayed in the Extended HE Just Intonation notation when selecting Just Intonation from the Style menu.</i></p>

<h2>Other keyboards</h2>
<illustration><img src="images/Microtones/micro-image5-BPji.png" width="300"/></illustration>
<p><i>A Bohlen-Pierce Just Intonation diamond created by Todd Harrop.</i></p>
<p><br/> </p>
<illustration><img src="images/Microtones/micro-image6-Other-Keyboards-Pitch-tool.png"/></illustration>
<p><i>User-created keyboard for the input of Easley Blackwood's study in 23TET.</i></p>
<p><br/>In order to listen to this piece, look for "Blackwood - 23 notes score.XML" in MaxScore 8/examples/Scores. Open MaxScore Combo and load this file in the Editor and then the 23-Tones.json preset file into the MaxScore.FluidSynth2 player. Start playback to experience multi-timbral music in non-standard tuning.</p>


</chapter>
