<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="./_c74_tut.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<chapter name="Playback in MaxScore">
<previous name="04maxscore-picster">MaxScore: Microtones</previous>
<next name="06maxscore-macaque">Macaque</next>

<parent name="00maxscore-00index">MaxScore: Table of Contents</parent>
<setdocpatch name="MaxScore-Playback" patch="MaxScore-Playback-Tutorial.maxpat"/>


<h1>Playback in MaxScore</h1>

<h2>maxscore.makenote</h2>
<p>As we have mentioned before, MaxScore is an environment designed for the notation and playback of microtones. We are therefore using a MIDI-like protocol which indicates pitch in MIDI cents.</p>
<p>The maxscore.makenote abstraction is used to convert the output of the MaxScore abstraction into the format understood by the MaxScore playback devices:</p>

<techdetail>
Note on: note 6000 78 1<br/>
Note off: note 6000 0 1
</techdetail>

<p>The three numbers denote pitch (in MIDI cents), velocity and channel.</p>
<p>The maxscore.makenote object also receives a dictionary containing the Picster expressions attached to notes and intervals. These expressions will be looked up during playback and sent out to the parent patcher via the second outlet.</p>

<h2>Playback Devices</h2>
Currently three playback devices are available for sound generation

<p>MaxScore/LiveScore Sampler and MaxScore/LiveScore Fluidsynth2 are two playback patches/devices that were especially designed for the MaxScore/LiveScore Editor and its microtonal capabilities. So far, the combination of Editor and Sampler and/or Fluidsynth is the only way to consistently compose and playback microtonal music in Ableton Live.</p>

<h3>Fluidsynth und Sound Fonts</h3>
<illustration><img src="images/playback/FluidSynth2.png" width="350"/></illustration>
<p><br/> </p>
<techdetail>
<p><b>The Fluidsynth2 player is capable of using an abundance of sound fonts available on the Net.</b></p></techdetail>
<p>In our tutorial patch you will see a score by the American composer Easley Blackwood in 23-tone equal temperament. Turn on audio and press the start button to begin playback. You can also experiment with setLoopingPlayback and setSection messages. To play a section use playSection message instead of start. Turn Overdrive on when you notice that playback is not even.</p>
<illustration><img src="images/playback/MaxScore-Playback-Tutorial.png"  width="900"/></illustration>

<h3>Sampler and Sample Banks</h3>
<illustration><img src="images/playback/MaxScore-Sampler.png" width="350"/></illustration>
<p>The Sampler uses a propriety text-based format with an built-in editor. There will be a separate tutorial on how to use the sampler and its GUI.</p>
<illustration><img src="images/playback/Sample-Editor-Window.png"  width="600"/></illustration>

<p><i><a href="http://georghajdu.de/computermusicnotation/wopre/wp-content/uploads/2012/08/Piano.zip">Download</a></i> a bank file with high-quality grand piano sounds sampled with and without pedal down. Used with kind permission from the Virtual Orchestra Collection (© Thomas Hummel).</p>
<techdetail>
<p>For your convenience, open the Combo template from Max File menu>New>From Template>MaxScore>Combo. It contains the Editor as well as two playback devices.</p>
</techdetail>

<h3>conTimbre Support</h3>
<p>The maxscore.2conTimbre interfaces with the conTimbre ePlayer and also opens its preset files. Go to <a href="https://www.contimbre.com/en">conTimbre</a> for more information on this sound library.</p>
<illustration><img src="images/playback/conTimbre.png" width="350"/></illustration>


</chapter>
