<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="./_c74_tut.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<chapter name="MaxScore: Compatibility">
<previous name="08maxscore-playback">MaxScore: Playback</previous>
<next name="06maxscore-macaque">Macaque</next>

<parent name="00maxscore-00index">MaxScore: Table of Contents</parent>
<!--
<setdocpatch name="MaxScore-API" patch="MaxScore-Export-Tutorial.maxpat"/>
-->

<h1>MaxScore: Compatibility with Other Software Solutions</h1>

<p>MaxScore is capable of importing from and exporting to various other software solutions.</p>
<h2>MIDI</h2>
<p>Like very other notation program, MaxScore is capable reading or writing MIDI files. The disadvantage of using MIDI is that the file is only capable of representing the absolute minimum of what makes up your score with no support for markings and graphics.</p>
<h2>musicXML</h2>
<p>musicXML is the de facto standard for exchanging files between notation programs. By supporting musicXML, MaxScore can open files created in Finale, MuseScore, Dorico or Sibelius as well as write files which can be imported by these software applications. Note that the features exported by MaxScore only represent a subset of MaxScore's feature set, particularly in the graphic domain. Therefore, some post-processing may be necessary to make the scores look like in the environment you exported from. </p>
<illustration><img src="images/Compatibility/musicxml2jmsl.js.png" width="500"/></illustration>
<center><i>The musicXML importer was written in node.js by John MacCallum</i></center>
<h2>LilyPond</h2>
<p>MaxScore is capable of exporting to LilyPond, a engraving program with many intelligent features for the automatic placement of score elements.</p>
<h2>Decible ScorePlayer</h2>
<p>The MaxScore Editor imports Decible ScorePlayer projects via the Scrolling Score Creator scorepion. For this, the ScorePlayer .dsz files need to be decompressed first by replacing the .dsz extension by .zip and using an unzipper to reveal the content of the project folder.</p>
<illustration><img src="images/Compatibility/ScrollingScoreCreator.png" width="900"/></illustration>
<i>MaxScore showing a score by Lindsay Vickery created for the Decibel ScorePlayer.</i>
<h2>bach.roll and bach.score</h2>
<p>The bach project is Max package for computer-assisted composition. Its bach.roll and bach.score objects are music notation editors for timed and proportional notation. They implement a Lisp-like language and pass messages in llll (Lisp-like linked lists) format. The maxscore.bachToMaxScore abstraction will take the output of the bach.score and bach.roll objects in its left and right inlets, resp., and translate it to MaxScore messages. As MaxScore can toggle between standard and proportional notation, the resulting score can look like the original bach.roll score.</p>
<illustration><img src="images/Compatibility/bachToMaxScore.png"/></illustration>
<i>The output of the bach.score and bach.roll objects can be imported into MaxScore via the maxscore.bachToMaxScore abstraction</i>
<h2>SVG support</h2>
<p>See <link type="tutorial" module="maxscore" name="11maxscore-export">MaxScore Editor: Exporting to SVG and PDF</link> for more information on SVG export.</p>
</chapter> 